[MUSIC]
[再現研究]
In this lecture
we'll talk about replication studies.
這一講要談再現研究
Replication studies where
you repeat an experiment
重覆一項實驗並嘗試獲得相同結果
是所有實證科學的基石
try to observe the same results are a
cornerstone of any empirical science.
重覆一項實驗並嘗試獲得相同結果
是所有實證科學的基石
At the same time they're quite
challenging to perform
研究者通常很難再現相同結果
they're not always rewarded
when people perform them.
也很難因為進行再現研究得到獎勵
When we look at the scientific literature
閱覽科學文獻會發現再現研究是
任何實證科學的基石
we see that replications are a cornerstone
of any empirical science.
閱覽科學文獻會發現再現研究是
任何實證科學的基石
This is nicely illustrated by
this quote by Karl Popper.
卡爾．波普的這段名言完整體現再現研究的重要性
Now whenever you sight(cite) Popper
people have to take you seriously
任何有引述波普的文章，論述彷彿有一定份量
So let's take a look what Popper
says about replication studies.
就來看看波普怎麼談再現研究
He says only when certain events
recur in accordance with rules or
「只有當一定事件一致於規則或」
(翻譯參考陳瑞麟「科學哲學：理論與歷史」p.106)
regularities
with repeatable experiments
「規律性而重現時，如同可重複的實驗案例」
(翻譯參考陳瑞麟「科學哲學：理論與歷史」p.106)
can our observations be tested
in principle by anyone.
「我們的觀察原則才能被他人檢驗」
(翻譯參考陳瑞麟「科學哲學：理論與歷史」p.106)
We do not take even our own
observations quite seriously or
「除非能被重複檢驗，我們無法嚴肅看待」
(翻譯參考陳瑞麟「科學哲學：理論與歷史」p.106)
accept them as scientific observations
until we have repeated and tested them.
「自己的觀察或者視之為科學事實」-
(翻譯參考陳瑞麟「科學哲學：理論與歷史」p.106)
Only by such repetitions can we convince
ourselves that we are dealing with events
「如此，我們有足夠理由根據事件之間的」
(翻譯參考陳瑞麟「科學哲學：理論與歷史」p.106)
which on account of their regularity and
「規律性與可重製性，」
(翻譯參考陳瑞麟「科學哲學：理論與歷史」p.106)
reproducibility
inter-subjectively testable.
「處理互為主體可檢驗的事件。」
(翻譯參考陳瑞麟「科學哲學：理論與歷史」p.106)
We've been talking a lot about
calculating statistics and
至此已談過許多估計實驗結果信度的統計技術
estimating the reliability of findings.
But the real test is really
whether a study replicates.
然而最實際的信度測試是檢驗可否再現實驗結果
If someone else reproduces your
study does everything exactly
有什麼方式比其它人能重製你的研究過程
並得到相同結果更令人可信？
the same as you did it
will they observe the same results?
有什麼方式比其它人能重製你的研究過程
並得到相同結果更令人可信？
Now this became a hot topic after the
publication by Darrel Bem of the set of
Dareel Bem發表一系列超感知覺實驗之後
再現研究如今已是熱門議題
studies that examines precognition.
Dareel Bem發表一系列超感知覺實驗之後
再現研究如今已是熱門議題
So there's a set of studies where people
are seemingly able to predict the future.
這一系列研究顯示普通人似乎有能力預測未來
And of course here
effect it's immensely important.
如果研究發現的確為真，會是很重要的議題
If people can really predict the future
we want to know.
如果人人都能預測未來，你我都想知道怎麼回事
So immediately after this publication
people set out to try to replicate
自從Bem的研究發表之後，很多研究者嘗試再現他們的發現
the studies.
This is one example of a study
that tries to replicate
這篇論文是嘗試再現Bem的發現的眾多研究之一
the original observations by Daryl Bem.
The title already gives it away.
論文標題相當直白
Failing the future
Three unsuccessful attempts to replicate
看不到未來：無法成功再現Bem的回溯促進記憶效果的三筆實驗
Bem's Retroactive Facilitation
of recall effect.
看不到未來：無法成功再現Bem的回溯促進記憶效果的三筆實驗
So these researchers
did everything more or
論文作者們儘可能以Daryl Bem的方法進行實驗
less the same as Daryl Bem
did in his original studies.
論文作者們儘可能以Daryl Bem的方法進行實驗
But they did not observe
a precognition effect.
卻沒有發現任何超感知覺效果
I want to point out that this publication
appeared in the journal PLOS one.
值得注意的是這篇論文發表在PLOS ONE
PLOS one is a groundbreaking journal
that publishes any effect or
PLOS ONE是以研究的設計完善程度
而非實驗效果是否顯著為接受標準的著名期刊
any set of studies as long as
the studies are well designed.
PLOS ONE是以研究的設計完善程度
而非實驗效果是否顯著為接受標準的著名期刊
Now you might think
what's so special about that?
為何要特別提出來說？
But it means that they also
publish replication studies.
不就是PLOS ONE也會接受再現研究
Again you might think
what's special about that
這篇論文為何值得一提？
shouldn't any scientific journal
publish replication studies?
不是任何科學期刊都會出版再現研究嗎？
But this is not the case.
很不幸不是如此
It turns out that these
authors first submitted
這要從這幾位作者最早投稿的故事講起
their replication studies to the same
journal as the original study appeared in.
一開始他們投到Daryl Bem發表原始研究的期刊
(人格與社會心理學期刊)
Elliot Smith
the Journal of Personality and
當時的期刊主編Elliot Smith拒絕了這篇論文
Social Psychology rejected the submission.
He said
the journal of Bem replications.
他表示這本期刊無必要成為再現Bem的研究專刊
So he rejected these replication studies
所以他拒絕了這些再現研究
because he didn't want to be a journal
that publishes replications.
因為他不希望這本期刊只出版再現研究
The field criticized this decision.
他的決定引起社會心理學界的一陣議論
The idea is that if replications are so
important for science
再現研究對科學進展的重要性若是科學家的普遍信念
journals that publish original results
should also publish well designed and
出版原始研究的期刊應該也要出版有良好設計與明確結果的再現研究
well performed replication studies.
In this publication
in the field are quickly evolving.
至於這篇論文則體現社會心理學界迅速變遷的價值觀
This publication
the Past: Failures to Replicate Psi
這篇「修正過去–再現超能力實驗的失敗案例」
is a set of studies where researchers
again tried to replicate the original
是另一系列嘗試再現Daryl Bem原始發現的研究
studies by Daryl Bem
to find any effect for precognition.
這份研究也無法發現任何相同的超感知覺效應
The only change here is that these
studies appeared in the same journal
與前一篇再現研究的不同之處是
where Daryl Bem published his research.
這篇論文被接受
We now see that many journals
explicitly invite replication studies
如今許多期刊以實際行動歡迎任何不管有無註冊的再現研究
pre-registered or not.
So this is a real improvement
in the recent years.
這些年的確有許多實際的進展
People are starting to value replication
studies more than they did in the past.
很多學者開始重新評價再現研究的重要性
Now if replication studies are so
important
談到這裡你也許會想，科學界應該有如何進行再現研究的完整規則
that we have a very clear set of rules
of how to perform these studies
談到這裡你也許會想，科學界應該有如何進行再現研究的完整規則
this is not the case.
然而實情不是如此
How we should perform replication
studies is a very active
如何進行再現研究是一門正在開始摸索
也存在許多爭議的科學議題
ongoing debate in
the literature at this moment.
如何進行再現研究是一門正在開始摸索
也存在許多爭議的科學議題
Now you might think
if these studies are so
你也許好奇，如果再現研究這麼重要
一百年前應該就有科學家開始進行了
very important
about how to do this 100 years ago?
你也許好奇，如果再現研究這麼重要
一百年前應該就有科學家開始進行了
I don't know.
老實說我不知道一百年前
But now
至少現在，我們正在解決設計良好再現研究的問題
we're addressing the questions of how
to do an adequate replication study.
至少現在，我們正在解決設計良好再現研究的問題
Now when you try to do a replication
若你想進行一項再現研究
the first thing to realize is that there
is no such thing as an exact replication.
首先要了解世上沒有精準的再現研究(exact replication)
You can never really repeat everything
in exactly the same manner.
沒有人能百分之百再現原始研究的細節
You're studying real life people.
因為行為科學的對象是活生生的人類
Times are changing.
人類都會隨時間改變
There's always some minor variation.
實驗結果永遠都會有些微的變化
We can distinguish between
a direct replication.
能做的一種再現研究是「直接再現」
So even though it's not identical
in this case
直接再現不盡然與原始研究完全相同
you're trying to stick as closely
as possible to the original study.
而是盡可能接近原始研究
You're keeping everything that
you think matters the same.
在能力及資源所及範圍之內達到相同的條件
You can also perform
a conceptual replication or
另一種再現研究是「概念再現」
as we might call it
a theoretical reproduction.
也有人叫「理論重製」
We already see that you're not doing
exactly the same in exactly the same way
由於沒人能做到完全精確的再現
but here you are testing the theoretical
idea in a slightly novel way.
就用稍微不同的方式檢驗理論的真實性
You are changing things in the study
design or in the manipulations.
研究的設計或變項操作會有些許不同
But you are trying to test
the same underlying hypothesis.
但是都是要測試同一種理論
The goals of doing
replication studies are many.
再現研究有許多要完成的目標
The first is identifying type 1 errors.
首要是確認研究的型一錯誤率
Now if you've set your type 1 error
rate to 5%
設定型一錯誤率為5%是指重覆研究多次之後
如果實驗效果並不存在卻顯示顯著結果的比率不超過5%
something when there is nothing a maximum
of 5% of the time
設定型一錯誤率為5%是指重覆一項實驗多次之後
如果實驗效果並不存在卻顯示顯著結果的比率不超過5%
So the goal of a replication
studies to identify
這個目標是評估文獻報告結果的偽陽性
these false positives in the literature.
And this is of course very important
because we want to know that
了解文獻的可信度是設計再現研究的首要動機
the data in the published
literature is reliable.
了解文獻的可信度是設計再現研究的首要動機
The second goal is controlling for
artifacts.
其次是控制人為因素
Sometimes there might be a lack
of internal validity in a study.
這是出於研究可能缺乏內在效度的考量
You've used a very specific
type of stimuli for example.
也許原始研究一開始使用一群字詞
One set of words
you might want to do a replication with
a slightly different set of words.
之後的再現研究使用不同的另一群字詞
Or maybe you even want to use
pictures instead of words.
甚至用圖片取代字詞
This shouldn't really matter for
the basic effects
材料的差別對實驗效果的影響無足輕重
it increases the internal
validity of the study.
確能增加研究的內在效度
Third goal is to generalize
to new populations.
第三點是測試實驗效果透過不同樣本再現
One criticism in psychology
心理學最常遇到的批判是多是研究都是招募在學學生擔任受試者
is that a lot of the research that's
being done is performed on students.
心理學最常遇到的批判是多是研究都是招募在學學生擔任受試者
These are typically highly educated.
通常都是大學生
They come from Western
democratic universities.
許多研究出自西方民主國家的大學院校
So sometimes
有時候研究者會想實驗效果會不會在不同的參與者身上有不同發現？
does this affect generalize to
completely different populations?
有時候研究者會想實驗效果會不會在不同的受試身上有不同發現？
And you might want to do almost
exactly the same study but
此時就會想找不同文化背景的受試者做再現研究
just on different culture for example.
The fourth goal is especially for
conceptual replications.
第四個目標是概念再現特別重視的理由
Here
the underlying hypothesis.
就是檢驗潛在的假設
If this prediction halts
also observe a slightly different effect
如果同樣的理論能預測不同情況的結果，
應該能在稍微不同的研究條件發現另一種結果
in slightly different study that is
based on the same theoretical idea.
如果同樣的理論能預測不同情況的結果，
應該能在稍微不同的研究條件發現另一種結果
Now it's important to perform
these replication studies.
了解進行再現研究的重要性之後
You might think why bother.
你也許好奇為何要如此大費周章
Everything that's in the published
literature should be extremely
已經發表的文獻不是已經相當可信了？
reliable
We only have a 5% type 1 error rate
so how much can be wrong?
只設定5%的型一錯誤率怎麼可能還會出錯？
It turns out that it's quite likely
that studies do not replicate.
然而這些研究的結論未經再現研究證實之前
仍有出錯的可能
We don't know exactly how likely but
出錯的可能性有多高無法得知
there's some examples that
are reason enough to worry.
但是有些案例讓人必須擔心
For example
studies
像是癌症新藥如此人命關天的研究課題
So these are studies that are trying to
address new medicine for cancer research.
這類研究要測試新藥的抗癌效果
In this field
researchers who tried to replicate
曾有研究者嘗試再現53項有可信度，但是相當新穎的研究
a set of 53 very promising
but also very novel
曾有研究者嘗試再現53項有可信度，但是相當新穎的研究
Of this only six
could successfully be replicated.
結果只有其中6項，也就是11%的再現率
Now this is a company trying to build on
scientific research and you know that if
這項研究是一間公司為了投資而進行的再現研究
they succeed in replicating these studies
they will make a lot of money.
如果成功再現就能獲得巨大報酬
But even
despite their very high motivation
儘管每項研究的動機都是為了救人，結果卻只有11%的可再現率
only six out of 53 studies
successfully reproduce.
儘管每項研究的動機都是為了救人，結果卻只有11%的可再現率
So this is a reason to worry.
值得省思這類研究的可再現率有多高
In psychology there was a large
scale replication project
在這項大規模的心理學再現研究專案
where 100 studies in the published
literature from 2008 from three main
召集世界各地260多位心理學者
journals were reproduce by over 260
different researchers working in teams.
再現100項在2008年發表於三本重要期刊的研究
They reproduced 100 studies.
100項研究的再現結果並非全部都能成功再現
And when they replicated these studies
not all of them successfully replicate.
100項研究的再現結果並非全部都能成功再現
It's very difficult to say how many
depends on the threshold that you want to
然而定義再現結果是否成功的標準相當困難
define for a replication.
Is this a significant effect?
怎麼算是一種顯著效果？
Is it a similar effect
of the similar size?
是以接近的樣本數得到相似的效果嗎？
Let's take a look at the p-value
distribution of the effects
來看看所有實驗結果的p值分佈
from the original studies and from
the effects in the replication studies.
左邊來自原始研究，右邊來自再現研究
On the left here we see the p-value
distribution and on the vertical axis
圖左側的縱軸由下至上標示的p值從0到1
we have the p-values ranging from
zero on the bottom to one on the top.
圖左側的縱軸由下至上標示的p值從0到1
Non-surprisingly
almost all of the published
毫無意外地，因為出版偏誤的關係，
所有原始研究的p值都小於0.05
studies yielded p-values
that were smaller than 0.05.
毫無意外地，因為出版偏誤的關係，
所有原始研究的p值都小於0.05
On the right
distribution of replication studies
右邊再現研究的p值分佈從0到1都有
which are all over the place.
Purely based on p-values
about 40% of the studies replicate it.
只以p值來看，只有40%的再現研究是成功的
Again
再次提醒，這不是說原始研究的理論是錯的
(見第一週第二講)
underlying these original
studies is not true.
再次提醒，這不是說原始研究的理論是錯的
(見第一週第二講)
A failed replication does not
falsify an entire theory.
一次失敗的再現不足以否證整個理論
There can be many reasons
why replication fails.
有許多能解釋為何再現失敗的原因
Of course
what these reasons could be.
當然我們必須好好想想到底是什麼原因
But it's too early to
dismiss all these studies.
不過現在不是無視這些研究的時候
Nevertheless a replication
rate of around 40% is
雖然只有40%成功再現似乎不令人滿意
not as high as you would like it to be.
So which studies might
be especially troubling?
那麼究竟是那些研究很可能無法再現？
In a Bayprint 2015
Lindley called this the Troubling Trio
Lindley提出可能無法再現的研究具備的三種特徵
three aspects of studies that should
make you slightly more doubtful.
只要三者皆具，你應該要質疑這一系列研究結果
The first is low power small simple sizes.
第一點是低統計考驗力且效果量微小
The second is relatively high p-value and
as we saw in the lecture on
第二點是相對高的p值，
就像第五週第三講的p curve所述那樣
p-value distributions and in the lecture
on p curve analysis this make sense.
第二點是相對高的p值，
就像第五週第三講的p curve所述那樣
The last one is a surprising result.
最後一點是令人驚奇的結果
And as we saw in the lecture
on Bayesian statistics
就像前幾週談貝式統計提到的
this is also a valid reason to
doubt the original finding.
是可以合理懷疑原始研究真實性的理由
So whenever there was a small sample size
a relatively high p value
只要看到一項研究有小樣本，高p值，
與令人驚奇的結果
a surprising result
we can refer to this as a troubling trio.
就可以懷疑這項研究的結果
And we should be slightly more
skeptical about these studies.
而且應該對一系列的結果保持起碼的懷疑
And it's definitely worthwhile to try
to replicate these studies before you
在進行再現研究之前，這些是值得檢視的重點
try to build on them.
Now in recent years
近幾年出現許多大規模再現研究專案
we see an increase in what you would call
large scale reproducibility projects.
近幾年出現許多大規模再現研究專案
Metascience could rescue the replication
crisis
就像Jonathan Schooler指出這類研究能挽救再現危機
He's referring to what's known as
registered replication reports.
他的說法來自自己的研究被註冊再現研究成功再現
(參考https://osf.io/ybeur/)
In these studies
labs collaborate together
這些註冊再現研究是針對同一項研究的跨實驗室合作
(參考http://scchen.com/Text/text_2016004/)
they replicate one study.
這些註冊再現研究是針對同一項研究的跨實驗室合作
(參考http://scchen.com/Text/text_2016004/)
So
where 100 studies are replicated one time
不像前述100項研究只由一個實驗室再現一項研究
in these situations
different labs replicate the same study.
參與專案的所有實驗室同步再現同一項實驗
So
因此能累積可觀的資料
Let's take a look at
one of these data sets.
就拿其中一件專案來看看
The many labs project
where a set of studies was replicated
2014年發表的多實驗室再現專案，
就是各實驗室再現一系列實驗
here we see what's known as
a prospective meta analysis.
並且以所謂的前瞻性整合分析整理結果
The researchers decided that they would
combine all the studies that individual
研究者們結算所有單一實驗室的結果
再計算出各項研究的整合分析效果量
researchers did
calculate a meta analytical effect size.
研究者們結算所有單一實驗室的結果
再計算出各項研究的整合分析效果量
So these are replications of the same
study by many different labs
圖中每一條水平線代表一項實驗的所有實驗室結果
all over the world.
And if a result is statistically
significance in these studies
如果一項結果是統計顯著的
we can be fairly confident
that this is true effect.
就會看到水平線顯示該項研究的真實效果
We have so much data that this kind of
replication projects really tell us
有如此多資料的再現研究有助評估原始研究效果為真的機率
something about the probability
that the original study is true.
有如此多資料的再現研究有助評估原始研究效果為真的機率
Now if you want to build on the published
literature it's always smart
如果要根據已知的文獻進行研究
to perform what's known as
a replication and extension study.
最聰明的辦法是進行再現與擴充研究
You replicate the original result
除了再現原始研究結果，也進行新的實驗
you create some sort of addition
something new.
除了再現原始研究結果，也進行新的實驗
You add a condition where you change
something about the stimuli or
像是改變刺激或增加實驗操作條件
about about the manipulation.
So in this cases
is successful but the extension is not
這種情況下如果再現成果
但是新條件沒有顯著結果
successful
the novel thing that you introduced.
也有好的理由說明預測的新效果為何不會出現
If you cannot reproduce the original
result
如果無法再現原始研究的結果，也不必質疑理論是否正確
your new idea but you should have
more doubt about the original study.
而是要懷疑原始研究有什麼問題
If we really want to know
whether results are reliable
想知道一種實驗結果是否可信
it's essential that they can
be replicated by other labs.
必須讓不同實驗室成功再現
Replication studies are a cornerstone
of any empirical science.
再現研究是任何實證科學的基石
[MUSIC]
[課程結束]